PRANAY SINGH PARIHAR

DEVOPS ENGINEER

Contact Info

7568591982 pranaysparihar@gmail.com

SUMMARY

I am an experienced DevOps Engineer, with experience working on major cloud providers like AWS, Azure and GCP withholding the certifications as well and with expertise on CI/CD tools like Terraform and Ansible along with git and Azure DevOps.

WORK EXPERIENCE

Project Lead NCR Corporation Dec 2021 - present

Installing Prometheus Operator with Grafana Cloud for Kubernetes:

- Utilized Ansible to manage Kubernetes resources, ensuring consistent and reproducible deployments.
- Develop a dedicated Ansible role for Prometheus Operator installation, configuration and updates.
- Automated checks for overall cluster health to identify potential issues.
- Monitored resource consumption, including pod resource usage and storage utilization.
- Deployed Prometheus Operator on Kubernetes to monitor cluster health, node performance and resource utilization.
- Implemented custom Prometheus exporters for application to capture and analyze application-specific metrics, such as request latency, error rates, and throughput.
- Integrated Grafana Cloud for advanced visualization of Prometheus metrics, creating custom dashboards tailored to different stakeholders.
- Established a robust CI/CD pipeline using Github Actions for automated testing and Deployment of monitoring configurations.
- Integrated User Management Dashboard for Auth0 and Datadog:
 - Lead a team of five people to create a dashboard that invites, deletes as well as list users to our Auth0 and Datadog portal.

- Integrated backend functionality using Flask, Python
- Utilized Axios Library to handle asynchronous HTTP requests and ensure seamless data retrieval and updates.
- Implemented NgxSpinner Service to display loading spinners during time-consuming operations, enhancing user experience.
- Collaborated with the team to identify and resolve technical issues, ensuring smooth application perfromace.
- Utilized Git and GitHub for version control, ensuring efficient code collaboration and management.
- Defined infrastructure as code using Terraform configuration files to provision AWS Amplify resources.
- Designed and structured Terraform modules to promote reusability and maintainability of infrastructure code, allowing for easy replication across multiple projects.
- Utilized Terraform workspaces and variables to manage environment-specific configurations, enabling the deployment of different environments with minimal manual interventions.
- Integrated Terraform with Gtihub to track infrastructure changes and facilitate collaborative development with the team.
- Conducted thorough testing and validation of the terraform scripts to ensure the correctness and reliability of the infrastructure deployments.

DevOps Engineer

NCR Corporation

Dec 2021 – March2023

- Worked on groovy scripts to invoke functions on remote server for Jenkins pipeline.
- Experience designing terraform and deploying it in cloud deployment manager to spin up resources like virtual private cloud, Elastic compute resources with autoscaling.
- Setup GCP firewall rules in order to allow or deny traffic to and from the VMs based on specific configuration and use GCP Cloud DNS to deliver content from GCP cache locations drastically improving user experience and latency.
- Experience in Blue/Green deployment strategy by creating new applications which are identical to the existing production environment using CloudFormation templates and Route53 weighted record sets to redirect traffic from the old environment to the pristine environment via DNS.

DevOps Engineer IbexLabs Nov2021 - Dec2021

- Working on Ansible scripts to install Cloudwatchagenton EC2 instances and monitor metrics like Volumeusage, memoryusage and CPUusage
- Setting up multiple environment variables input on GitHub to deploy images to ECR.

DevOps Engineer TwimBit Sept2021 - Oct2021

- Setup CloudFront along with Application LoadBalancers for ECS.
- Setup Task definitions for a Caddy server and staticwebsite.
- Write Nginx configuration to reverse proxy traffic within the cluster and to serve SSL certificate on thego with the help of OpenResty Framework.
- Managing the entire infrastructure using terraform. Setup Lambda function for database failover and automate the process using step functions.
- Setup A records and CNAME in Route53.

DevOps Engineer Neudesic Mar2021 - Aug2021

- Created a Windows server image using Hashicorp Packer.
- Deploying the Packer image on Azure Virtual MachineScale Set using Terraform.
- Managing a GKE cluster using Terraform.
- Setup Load Balancer for the Kubernetes Cluster.

DevOps Intern Tivona Global Oct2020- Feb2021

- Continuous deployment automation using bash scripting.
- Automated AWS cloud deployment using Terraform from scratch.
- Implemented sentinel policies on Terraform Cloud.
- Using dynamic blocks to dynamically create multiple resources of block within a resource from a complex value such as a list of map.
- Create IAM policies for users and attach them to an IAM group.
- Lambda function to attach the IAM policy to an IAM user and save the CloudTrail logs for IAM user in DynamoDB using Boto3 scripting.

TECHNOLOGIES

SOFTWARE

Microsoft Teams

VS Code

Slack

Amazon Web Services

Terraform

Git

Python

Azure DevOps

Google Cloud Platform Azure

Docker

Bash

IAM

AWS Lambda

RBAC

EDUCATION HISTORY

Bachelor Of TechnologyVIT University, Chennai2017 - 2021

- Under Graduated in Electrical and Electronics Engineering.
- Studied electrical machines, control systems, and signals and systems.

ACHIEVMENTS

Recognized as a Terraform Subject Matter Expert:

- · Recognized as Terraform Subject Matter Expert
- Recognized by Neudesic as a Subject Matter expert for my work with Microsoft
- · Helped with internal projects of Neudesic

Tier-1 Udemy Course

- · Recognized as a Terraform Udemy Instructor.
- Authored practice questions for the Terraform associate exam.
- Regarded as the second-largest question bank for practice available online.
- My course got recognized as a tier-1 course on the Udemy platform

CERTIFICATIONS

Amazon Web Services:

Microsoft:

Terraform:

AWS Cloud Practitioner

Solutions Architect

AZ-900

 Terraform Certified Cloud Associate

IBM:

Istio and IBM Cloud

Kubernetes Service

Aviatrix:

Aviatrix

Certified

Engineer

Google Cloud Platform:

Digital Cloud Leader